Guide to the Listen to This: Crown Heights Oral History collection 2010.020
Brooklyn Historical Society
Listen to This: Crown Heights Oral History collection
2010
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn College
Brooklyn Historical Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Crow Hill Community Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Kelly, Alexandra
Paul Robeson High School (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
2010.020
15.9 Gigabytes in 187 files, total running time: 21 hours, 17 minutes, 51 seconds; .21 linear feet in 1 document box
This collection of forty-three oral history interviews with Brooklyn's Crown Heights neighborhood residents was donated to the Brooklyn Historical Society by project director Alexandra Kelly. The interviews were conducted in 2010 with the help of the Crow Hill Community Association and five students from Paul Robeson High School who came to the project through the Brooklyn College Community Partnership (BCCP). Included are perspectives from community activists, artists, business owners, retirees and young people. Many are native to the New York metropolitan area. Several others have come from other states, as well as Caribbean nations and Central American countries. Narrators discuss the history of Crown Heights, their childhood and schooling, the changing landscape and ethnic makeup of the community over decades, their parenting and careers, volunteerism and activism, and mentoring or advising young people.
Biographical / Historical
History of Crown Heights: From the late nineteenth century up to the World War I era, the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights was known for being an upper and upper middle class residential enclave. Russian Jews, Irish, and Italians moved there as a part of the boom in immigration from 1880 to 1940. Smaller migrations to Crown Heights occurred as well, with Caribbean migrants among these. Seeing an opportunity for first-time home ownership, some of Harlem's African American residents moved to the neighborhood in the 1930s. A great wave of Caribbean immigration followed in the 1960s and 1970s. With many White residents removing to the suburbs, those immigrants along with Caribbean Americans and African Americans invested and lived in the majority of residences from the 1960s to the 1990s. The Lubavitcher Hasidim, a Judaic movement that established its headquarters in Crown Heights in 1940, accounted for about eight percent of the population, according to 1990s figures. In 1991, long simmering tensions between members of the Lubavitcher and Black communities, and two fatalities, propelled the neighborhood into three days of unrest and violence. Encapsulated by the news media as the "Crown Heights Riot," the community took years to heal. Another demographic shift began as the 1990s ended; and - by the time these interviews had been recorded in 2010 - a new confluence of amenities, development, and rising property values was affecting the diverse face of the roughly 130,000 residents.
Listen to This: Crown Heights Oral History: In January 2010, StoryCorps alum and Crown Heights resident Alex Kelly met with five interns from Paul Robeson High School as placed by the Brooklyn College Community Partnership. Narrators were gathered primarily through contact with the Crow Hill Community Association and recorded in their homes or at LaunchPad, a community center on Franklin Avenue in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. New York City Grassroots Media Coalition sponsored the project. A blog tracking the progress of the oral histories was created by the interviewers: http://crownheightshistoryproject.blogspot.com/
Scope and Contents
Listen to This: Crown Heights Oral History includes interview audio and summaries created and collected within the context of a community project undertaken by project director Alex Kelly and Paul J. Robeson High School interns Treverlyn Dehaarte, Ansie Montilus, Monica Parfait, Quanaisha Phillips and Floyya Richardson. These interviewers recorded conversations with forty-three narrators. In addition to the educational experience for the student interns, the oral histories were conducted as life history and community anthropology interviews. Topics of discussion include family and parenting, migration, cultural and racial relations, occupations and business, education and religion, housing and gentrification, civil unrest and reconciliation, and community activism.
Arrangement
Listen to This: Crown Heights Oral History was kept in the original order, arranged alphabetically by the narrator's last name.
Related Materials
In addition to this collection, Brooklyn Historical Society has oral history collections and other records related to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn.
- The Crown Heights History Project collection includes thirty-three interviews conducted from 1993 to 1994. (1994.006)
- The West Indian Carnival Documentation Project Records includes thirty-four interviews dating from 1994 to 1995. (2010.019) - Also narrator Constance Lesold, the community activist recorded for this collection, is documented in the Eastern Parkway Coalition records, 1952-2007. (2007.016)
- 959 Park Place Tenants Association records (1978.009)
For more information on these collections please visit our online finding aid portal.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Alex Kelly donated copies of the oral history recordings and summaries to Brooklyn Historical Society in October 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the interviews is available onsite at the Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library and, in some instances, online on the Oral History Portal. Original summaries and biographic materials are accessible at the Othmer Library.
Oral History note
Oral history interviews are intimate conversations between people, all of whom have generously agreed to share these recordings with the Brooklyn Historical Society archives and with researchers. Please listen in the spirit with which these were shared. Researchers will understand that:
1. The Brooklyn Historical Society abides by the General Principles & Best Practices for Oral History as agreed upon by the Oral History Association (2009) and expects that use of this material will be done with respect for these professional ethics.
2. Every oral history relies on the memories, views and opinions of the narrator. Because of the personal nature of oral history, listeners may find some viewpoints or language of the recorded participants to be objectionable. In keeping with its mission of preservation and unfettered access whenever possible, BHS presents these views as recorded.
3. The audio recording should be considered the primary source for each interview. It may contain natural false starts, verbal stumbles, misspeaks, repetitions that are common in conversation.
4. Unless these verbal patterns are germane to your scholarly work, when quoting from this material researchers are encouraged to correct the grammar and make other modifications maintaining the flavor of the narrator's speech while editing the material for the standards of print.
Bibliography
Goldschmidt, Henry. Race and Religion Among the Chosen Peoples of Crown Heights New Brunswick, NJ: Rutgers University Press, 2006.
Gregor, Alison. "Crown Heights, Brooklyn, Where Stoop Life Still Thrives." New York Times. (New York, NY), June 17, 2015.
Shapiro, Edward S. Crown Heights: Blacks, Jews, and the 1991 Brooklyn Riot Waltham, MA: Brandeis University Press, 2006.
African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists; Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Girls |x Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Intergenerational relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Interviews (sound recordings); Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Judaism; Multiculturalism; Oral histories (document genres); Race identity; Schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Anonymous, 2010 May 26; 2010.020.001
  Biographical / Historical
  The narrator was born in Brooklyn to Orthodox Jewish parents. After youthful unruliness got her expelled from her Crown Heights Yeshiva in eighth grade, she attended a Jewish boarding school in Chicago where - under the mentorship of its principle - she responded well to the new surroundings and smaller class size. At the time of the interview the narrator had returned to Brooklyn, attended college and founded an outreach program for at-risk teens in her Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn.
  Scope and Contents
  In the interview the narrator recounts youthful memories, including a 1995 snow storm, as well as her experiences at the Chicago boarding school she attended after being ejected from her Brooklyn Yeshiva in eighth grade. The narrator discusses Jewish traditions and religious rituals in detail, in addition to her college career and interests. She discusses her current work with at-risk teens in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. Interview conducted by Ansie Montilus and Monica Parfait.
  Conditions Governing Access and Use
  Access to the interview is available onsite at the Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library. Use of the oral histories other than for private study, scholarship, or research requires the permission of BHS. For assistance, contact library@brooklynhistory.org.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Boarding schools |z United States; Chicago (Ill.); Hasidim |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Judaism |x Hasidic rite; Judaism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Synagogues |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Theology; Youthfulness; Hunter College; Schneerson, Menachem Mendel
- Atkins, Desmond, 2010 March 10; 2010.020.002
  Desmond Michael Atkins was born and raised in the central Brooklyn neighborhoods of Bedford-Stuyvesant and Crown Heights to parents of Barbadian and Panamanian descent. Atkins' childhood home, located at 122 Kingston Avenue near the corner of Bergen Street, was adjacent to historic Crown Heights' nightclub the Kingston Lounge. Having attended, but not completed college, the largely self-taught narrator worked for the United States Postal Service and as an information technologies professional in several businesses. At the time of the interview in 2010, Atkins - who expresses an avid interest in ethnic, regional and local history - continued to reside in Crown Heights.
  In the interview Desmond Atkins takes listeners on a personalized journey into New York's past, describing the dramatic economic, cultural, and educational changes that have occurred during his lifetime - a period that overlaps with the postwar decades of American history. He explains the musical and architectural significance of the historic Kingston Lounge nightclub. Atkins' narration pays special attention to Brooklyn's economic relationship to the surrounding region via traditional shipping routes and modes of travel. He attempts to contextualize this past with more recent events - namely the 2008 financial crisis and its fallout - as well as with the Crown Heights riot of 1991. Interview conducted by Floyya Richardson and Treverlyn Dehaarte.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Architecture |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x History |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews; Minorities |z United States |x Economic conditions; New York (N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Nightclubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Northeastern States |x Social life and customs; Popular music |z New York (State) |z New York; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z New York; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Atkins, Desmond
- Aubert, Maybell, 2010 April 14; 2010.020.003
  Maybell Aubert was born sometime before the end of World War II in Panama's Canal Zone, which at the time was a United States territory. She grew up speaking English and acquired Spanish as a second language while attending high school in Panama City. Along with her husband and children, Aubert moved to Brooklyn in the 1950s and has lived on St. Charles Street in Crown Heights since 1956. She graduated from Boys and Girls High School in Bedford-Stuyvesant and subsequently attended business school to train as an operator for the keypunch machine - a data processing device popular in offices through the 1970s. Upon retirement, Aubert continued her education at the City University of New York's Medgar Evers College. She has served as secretary of the St. Louis Senior Center where, at the time of the interview in 2010, she remains active. Having raised a family of accomplished children, Aubert is a proud great grandmother.
  Maybell Aubert recalls life in Panama's American-controlled Canal Zone - where the English language and American consumer products were the norm - as well as her move to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in the 1950s. Aubert relates descriptions of mom-and-pop businesses, Eisenhower-era prices and neighborhood institutions during the postwar period - including schools, hospitals, and Ebbets Field. She recounts her education and career as a key punch operator, as well as her post-retirement return to school. Aubert also discusses her involvement as a member of the St. Louis Senior Center, where she once served as secretary. She describes meeting her husband, raising a family and offers some advice on love and success. Interview conducted by Floyya Richardson, Treverlyn Dehaarte and Alex Kelly.
  Adult learning |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Girls |x Education (Secondary) |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Education, Higher |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (N.Y.); Office equipment and supplies; Panama; Panamanian Americans; Senior centers |z New York (State); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Aubert, Maybell; City University of New York. Medgar Evers College; Ebbets Field (New York, N.Y.)
- Beckford, Cynthia, 2010 March 31; 2010.020.004
  Cynthia Beckford was born in 1973 in Jamaica. Raised in the Jamaican countryside, at a young age Beckford had dreams of immigrating to urbane London, England. After a brief time spent in the care of an Indian woman who ran a hotel in Kingston, Jamaica she returned home for sewing school and a career as a dress maker. During a visit to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in the early 1980s, Beckford was awe-struck by its beauty, diversity and experienced a kind of déjà vu for her childhood fantasies of England. After a return to Jamaica, she applied for and was granted permanent resident status. With some help Beckford was able to obtain an apartment - as well as a new life for herself and her son - in Crown Heights.
  Cynthia Beckford remembers her childhood in rural Jamaica, her first impressions of - and first apartment in - the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, and her career as a skilled dress maker. She glowingly describes Crown Heights as a diverse, peaceful and beautiful residential enclave of New York City. Beckford recounts her first visits to the neighborhood, as well as her subsequent quest for permanent United States residence and employment. Beckford also recalls how after some early setbacks, perseverance, faith, and help from friends - as well as her labor union - she was able to secure a job and apartment, making a new life for herself and her son in a place where she feels blessed to be. Interview conducted by Alex Kelly.
  Access to the interview is available onsite at the Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library and online on the Oral History Portal. Use of the oral histories other than for private study, scholarship, or research requires the permission of BHS. For assistance, contact library@brooklynhistory.org.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans |x Relations with Jews; American Dream; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Clothing and dress |z New York (State) |z New York; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jamaican Americans; Jamaicans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Women |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions; Beckford, Cynthia
- Behrman, Michael, 2010 May 26; 2010.020.005
  Michael Behrman was born in Paterson, New Jersey in 1969. In 1976, after traveling and living in a number of different places, Behrman joined the Lubavitch sect of Orthodox Judaism. He made the conscious decision to trade his job in the film industry and home in Manhattan's Greenwich Village for a new life in Brooklyn's Crown Heights. Behrman was the director of a substance abuse prevention program for at-risk youth. At the time of the interview in 2010, he was married with four children and several grandchildren.
  Michael Behrman briefly describes the circumstances surrounding his religiously-motivated move to the Crown Heights section of Brooklyn, documenting some basic details of his earlier, more secular life and career in the motion picture industry. He goes on to describe events such as the 1977 New York City blackout, contrasting it with an earlier power outage in 1965, as well as the 1991 Crown Heights riot. He gives opinions on neighborhood affairs, city politics, theology and morality. Interview conducted by Treverlyn Dehaarte and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Electric power failures |z New York (State) |z New York; Hasidim |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Judaism |x Hasidic rite; Mayors |z New York (State) |z New York; New York (N.Y.); Theology; Behrman, Michael; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Dinkins, David N.; Giuliani, Rudolph W.; Schneerson, Menachem Mendel
- Bernadine, Melina, 2010 March 17; 2010.020.006
  Melina Bernadine was born in 1948 on the Caribbean island nation of Grenada. After marrying and having a son together, Melina and her husband immigrated to the United States in the late 1960s. They eventually settled in Crown Heights, Brooklyn and - against her spouse's advice - purchased a home as the 1970s progressed and New York City entered a period of decline. It was at that time that Bernadine took on an activist role in her neighborhood. Her two daughters both work full time helping to improve the lives of young people. At the time of the interview in 2010, Bernadine had resided in Crown Heights for thirty-two years.
  Melina Bernadine shares her experiences immigrating to the United States in the late 1960s - including her observations of crime and corruption in 1970s New York. She recounts buying a home and raising a family in Crown Heights, Brooklyn during an uncertain period of the city's history. Bernadine also touches on historical phenomena such as political activism in the 1960s and early 1970s, crime in New York City during the 1970s and 1980s, as well as the 1991 riot that seemed to serve as a turning point for both the neighborhood and the city. In 2010, Bernadine was still very much active in neighborhood affairs, attending precinct council meetings and offering advice to a younger generation. Interview conducted by Quanaisha Phillips, Floyya Richardson and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History |y 20th century; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z New York; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic relations; New York (N.Y.) |x History; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Political corruption |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Politicians |z New York (State); Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Urban beautification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bernadine, Melina; Black Panther Party; New York (N.Y.). Police Department
- Bogan, Ken, 2010 May 19; 2010.020.007
  Ken Bogan was born in Clarksville, Texas in 1958. On a trip to New York after completing graduate school at Duke University, he decided to stay and resided in the Upper Manhattan neighborhood of Washington Heights for one year, before moving to Crown Heights, Brooklyn in 1991. Bogan's father, who ran for mayor of their tiny Texas town, and grandfather - who was a union organizer - both taught him the importance of political activism at a young age. As a pastor, youth outreach worker and former political fundraiser, Bogan followed in his family footsteps. This journey would eventually lead him to the neighborhood at the time of the 1991 riot. As minister of the Greater Restoration Baptist Church and board member of Project CARE - which aims to bring together members of the Black and Hasidic communities - Bogan continues to work with Crown Heights residents.
  Pastor Ken Bogan shares details from his small town Texas childhood, as well as the highs and lows of his adult life and career. He recounts his first trip to New York after graduate school, his decision to stay and his early experiences as a seminary graduate-turned-community organizer. Pastor Bogan recalls moving to Crown Heights, Brooklyn during the apex of civil unrest in 1991 and his work trying to reconcile racial and cultural differences as well as foster new connections between the Black and Hasidic communities. He also reveals his past struggles with faith and predisposition for depression, in addition to offering advice on the importance of humility and communication. Interview conducted by Treverlyn Dehaarte and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Christian life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Migration, Internal |z United States; Multiculturalism; New York (N.Y.); Political participation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z United States; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Texas; Theology; Bogan, Ken; Fulani, Lenora
- Burnett, Collette, 2010 May 10; 2010.020.008